<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<Lesson>
<H>
<C> PowerShell Orientation </C>
<L> Variables </L>
</H>
<B>
<S> <N>Intro</N>
<t>
    You can store all types of values in Windows PowerShell variables. 
    They are typically used to store the results of commands and to 
    store elements that are used in commands and expressions, such as
    names, paths, settings, and values.
</t>
<t>
    A variable is a unit of memory in which values are stored. In Windows
    PowerShell, variables are represented by text strings that begin 
    with a dollar sign ($), such as $a, $process, or $my_var. 
</t>
<t>
    Variable names are not case-sensitive. Variable names can include
    spaces and special characters, but these are difficult to use and
    should be avoided.
</t>
</S>
<S> <N>Working with variables </N>
<t>
    To create a new variable, use an assignment statement to assign
    a value to the variable. You do not have to declare the variable
    before using it. The default value of all variables is $null.
</t>
<t> 
    For example, the following command stores a value of 5 in the variable v:

        PS> $v = 5
</t>
<t>
    After executing the command '$s = "Red"', what value is stored in the variable s?
    <opt>s</opt>
    <soln>Red</soln>
</t>
<t>    
    Variables are very useful for storing the results of commands. 
</t>
<t>
    For example, the following command stores the current number of seconds (0-59) of the current date and time
     
        PS> $s = (Get-Date).second
    <opt>cv</opt>
    <code>(Get-Date).second</code>
    <var>s</var>
</t>
<t>
    To display the value of a variable, type the variable name, preceded
    by a dollar sign ($). 
</t>
<t>
    For example:

        PS> $x = 5
        PS> $x 
        5
</t>
<t>
    The statement above :
    PS> $s = (Get-Date).second

    has been executed and the result has been saved in your environment

    What value is in s?
    <opt> pse </opt>
    <soln> $s </soln>
</t>

<t>
    To change the value of a variable, assign a new value to the variable. 
    This new value can be any type, since variables in Windows PowerShell
    are loosely typed. 
</t>
<t>
    For example, if we execute the following, a takes on 3 different values
      PS> $a = 5
      PS> $a = -3
      PS> $a = "bignum"
</t>
<t>
    What is the value of a after the previous statements have been executed?
    <opt>s</opt>
    <soln>"bignum"</soln>
</t>
<t>
    To delete the value of a variable, use the Clear-Variable cmdlet or 
    change the value to $null. 
</t>
<t>
        PS> Clear-Variable -name a  

        -or-

        PS> $a = $null
</t>
<t>
  Note that Clear-Variable requires the variable name without the '$', 
  whereas setting a variable to $null requires the use of the '$'.
</t>
<t>
    To delete the variable, use the Remove-Variable 
</t>
<t>
       PS> remove-variable -name a
</t>
<t>
  Here again, we use the variable name without the '$'.
</t>
<t>
    To get a list of all of the variables in your Windows PowerShell
    session, type:

       get-variable
    <opt>p</opt>
</t>
</S>
<S> <N>Types of variables </N>
<t>
    You can store any type of object in a variable, including integers, 
    strings, arrays, hash tables, and objects that represent processes, 
    services, event logs, and computers. 
</t>
<t>
    Windows PowerShell variables are "loosely typed," which means that
    they are not limited to a particular type of object. A single variable
    can even contain a collection (an "array") of different types of objects
    at the same time.
</t>
<t>
    The data type of a variable, which is a .NET Framework type, is
    determined by the .NET types of the values of the variable. 
</t>
<t>
    For example:

        PS> $a = 12     (System.Int32)
        
        PS> $a = "Word" (System.String)

        PS> $a = 12, "Word" (System.Int32, System.String)

        PS> $a = dir C:\Windows\System32  (Files and folders)
</t>
<t>
    You can use a type attribute and cast notation to ensure that a 
    variable can contain only objects of the specified type or objects 
    that can be converted to that type. If you try to assign a value
    of another type, Windows PowerShell tries to convert the value to
    its type. If it cannot, the assignment statement fails.
</t>
<t>
    To use cast notation, enter a type name, enclosed in brackets, before
    the variable name (on the left side of the assignment statement).
    The following example creates an $number variable that can contain
    only integers, a $words variable that can contain only strings, and
    a $dates variable that can contain only DateTime objects.
</t>
<t>
        PS> [int]$number = 8

        PS> $a = "12345" (The string is converted to an integer.)

        PS> $a = "Hello"
        Cannot convert value "Hello" to type "System.Int32". Error: "Input string was not in a correct format."

        PS> [string]$words = "Hello"

        PS> $words = 2   (The integer is converted to a string.)

        PS> $words + 10  (The strings are concatenated.)
        210              


        PS> [datetime] $dates = "09/12/91" (The string is converted to a DateTime object.)

        PS> $dates
        Thursday, September 12, 1991 12:00:00 AM

        PS> $dates = 10  (The integer is converted to a DateTime object.)
        PS> $dates
        Monday, January 01, 0001 12:00:00 AM
</t>             
</S>
<S> <N>Using variables in commands and expresions </N>    
<t>
    To use a variable in a command or expression, type the variable name, 
    preceded by the dollar sign ($). 
</t>
<t>
    If the variable name (and dollar sign) are not enclosed in quotation marks,
    or if they are enclosed in double quotation marks ("), the value of the
    variable is used in the command or expression. 
</t>
<t>
    If the variable name (and dollar sign) are enclosed in single quotation
    marks, ('), the variable name is used in the expression. 
</t>
<t>
    For example, the first command gets the value of the $profile variable,
    which is the path to the Windows PowerShell user profile file in the Windows
    PowerShell console. The second command opens the file in Notepad, and the
    third and fourth commands use the name of the variable in an expression.
</t>
<t>
        PS> $profile
        C:\Documents and Settings\User01\My Documents\WindowsPowerShell\Microsoft.PowerShell_profile.ps1

        PS> notepad $profile 
        - or -
        PS> notepad "$profile"
        C:\Documents and Settings\User01\My Documents\WindowsPowerShell\Microsoft.PowerShell_profile.ps1

        PS> '$profile'
        $profile

        PS> 'Use the $profile variable.'
        Use the $profile variable. 
</t>
</S>
</B>
</Lesson>